There's going to be an open source one.
Do you want it to be ours or do you want
it to be someone else's?
>> This is Brendan Burns, the co-creator of
Kubernetes, and I asked him about the
stories behind building it.
>> The hardest part actually of the project
was actually articulating that.
>> How long did that initial MVP take to
build?
>> I don't know, a little under a week,
maybe.
>> He had interesting career advice
grounded in his career story.
>> I believe you can hide order 10% of your
effort from your management.
>> Is there any upper bound where
Kubernetes just cannot handle that load?
>> Every time you change an order of
magnitude, the problem moves.
>> Here's the full episode.
I mean, let's start with Kubernetes cuz
that's super interesting. I don't I
don't fully understand the business
motivation. Like, let's say I was your
director or something like that and you
you came to me with this and you said,
"Hey, let's let's do this for everyone."
I don't fully understand what would be
in that strategy doc or that What would
you say in that meeting that would say,
"Here's the impact for Google if we
invest in building this for the the
industry?"
>> Yeah, it's funny cuz like the hardest
part actually of the project I would say
that in those early days was actually
articulating that.
Um and I think it was really clear in
our heads, but like figuring out how to
convince people
um
uh was tricky. Um and you know, I think
there was there were a variety of
different ways that we articulated why
it was important.
Um
one of them was uh related to the uh
MapReduce white paper.
Right? So, MapReduce at the time,
especially like Hadoop and big data were
were were a big deal. I think that, you
know, other things have kind of replaced
them at this point, but like MapReduce
was a big deal. Um and the the big data
revolution or whatever they called it.
Um
and you know, Google had written the
original white paper.
Um but Hadoop was an open source project
that Google had nothing to do with.
And got no credit for
it. And and and they just read the white
paper and they re-implemented it and
it's not the same. It's similar, but
it's not the same, right? Because
anytime you re-implement something, it's
not the same. And so part of the
argument was like, "Look, like
we have this cloud and we want to like
be influencing the technology
technological landscape if all we do is
kick out white papers,
we're not like if it doesn't run, if
it's not something that people can run,
they're not we're not going to be in the
driver's seat.
Um and so that was one of the one of the
one of the arguments. I think, you know,
the other couple arguments were like,
"Why containers? Why not why
why not you know, people are using VMs,
why containers?" And you know, a lot of
that was talking about like, "Look,
the demands of writing software and we
know internally, we know from doing this
internally that the demands of writing
reliable software necessitate having
systems that are sort of like autopilots
for your
um
you know, for your application. And and
we know that this is something that as
software becomes more and more critical
to more and more businesses, this is
something that you they're just going to
have to have, right? And so that's sort
of the why containers part. Um
and then
you know, I think that the third part
was the like why open source, right? And
in some sense, that's like the most
interesting conversation because people
are like, "Wow, this would be you know,
you've convinced me, right? Like you've
convinced me we should build it, we
should make it available to the world.
It's something that they're going to
find useful. Um but wouldn't it be so
much better if they could only use it on
our platform?"
And you're like, "Yeah, that's
absolutely the case,
but
you can't win if you make it only on
your platform."
>> Well, why is that?
>> Well, because there's other platforms
out there, right? And so, if you make it
an exclusive, then
the people who for other reasons are on
other clouds or on on-premise,
they're shut out.
And
so, they're going to just go build an
alternative.
Right? Like the like the the open source
the it's it's sort of like a Linux, you
know, uh the reason Linux won, right?
It's because Linux could go anywhere.
Right? The whole reason that open tech
and open ecosystems win is because
you the majority of people
are going to be not on your plat like if
you're if you're not the leader, and we
and you know, GCP was not the leader,
then the majority of people are not
going to be on your platform.
And so, if you make it such that the
majority of people can't use your thing,
they're just going to ignore you, and
then they're going to go build their
own.
Right? Whereas, if you go and build it
and you build it for everybody, but you
make sure that it's awesome on your
platform, then you have a chance of
attracting people attracting more people
to your platform,
uh than otherwise. And and then I mean,
also in some ways it's just like the
aesthetic of the time, also, right? It's
like if everybody's using Linux, and
everybody's using Docker, and
everybody's using these programming
languages that are all open, like if
everything else is open source,
you don't want to be the thing that's
not.
Right? And and there's only a few places
where like
where that hasn't been true historically
in technology, where you could be
different and still succeed, and you
have to be so differentiated
that and I don't think that we were
different that differentiated. You have
to be so differentiated such that people
are like, "Oh, actually, I want that
thing so bad, I don't care that it's
closed."
>> So, at the time just thinking what was
the competitive landscape, I guess
if I if I remember, it was I mean, AWS
was dominant. They were there first and
doing very well. GCP at that time
probably an up-and-coming company uh or
I guess offering.
And so, am I understanding then that the
idea is let's pull market share away by
giving kind of open source distributing
Kubernetes to more and more developers
and then they'll be more open to kind of
migrating or using GCP because you'll
make a
>> They'll pay attention. Right, they'll
pay attention. And also like you change
the dialogue too, right? Like tail light
chasing is hard.
Right? Like if if someone else has built
VMs and everybody's using VMs and all
you're doing is saying like, "Well,
we're building the same thing that they
have
only maybe it's a little bit better
because we do something else over here
or you know, whatever." Like that's a
hard market strategy to articulate. But
if you create a brand new playing field
where you are the thought leader
um
suddenly like people are listening to
you. Even if they're not using it on
your platform, they're listening to you
and that gives you way more voice. You
get you get a lot more voice in the
market. It changes the narrative. It
changes who people are listening to.
Um and so that control of of
the story is an important aspect of of
of how I think how you
break through that or you try to break
through that dynamic. Obviously, like
you know, they're still in third at this
point. So like
didn't work out, but um I mean, I
wouldn't say it didn't work out. I think
it worked out in general, but it's still
hard. Like overcoming those kinds of
market dynamics is hard and you know, I
think the other thing that happened is
everybody in the cloud consolidated
around it and so now Kubernetes is just
sort of a utility everywhere.
>> You you mentioned that I guess that
perception benefit of being at the
dominant offering. Um which I mean, if
you if you look at what happened in
hindsight, it makes a lot of sense. I
mean, that is what happened and it's
it's uh a wonderful benefit. But I guess
when you were looking forward and you
were talking to leadership were you
cognizant of those benefits and saying,
"We need to do this because
we're going to kind of become the
dominant offering and it's going to have
all these
uh optics benefits.
>> I mean, I think we absolutely wanted to
make sure that we were front and center
in terms of thought leadership and we
definitely articulated that. Right?
Absolutely right. Like being being in a
thought leadership position is value is
valuable.
>> It's interesting cuz um I feel like it's
hard to quantify. I mean, if I was in
that meeting and we're trying to make a
call
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> how much is that worth?
>> Yeah. Well, I think you have to also
realize that at the time like it was
pretty cheap, right? It was like eight
or nine engineers.
And and we kind of and this is in some
sense I mean it's both a blessing and a
curse. Like part of the reason why we
articulated and argued for having such a
distinct brand
where the Kubernetes brand was separated
from the Google brand um
was that it kind of gave us freedom to
fail also. It was like, "Hey, if these
eight people go off and you know, do
something and and it turns out to be
stupid, like
we'll just kill it off and it won't have
like it won't you know, it won't um it
won't damage the broader perception of
the cloud. And so I think there's
there's that benefit of the open source
part of it, too.
Um it helped with adoption, right? Like
it helped
it helped us and especially as we went
to like the Linux Foundation and things
like that and truly established like an
independent entity, it helped ensure
that you know, people like Red Hat or
Azure or AWS could take a bet on
Kubernetes and feel confident in that
bet. Um but it also was an insurance
policy against failure. And and also to
be honest like it was it it simplified a
lot of things, too, because
you know, we were competing against
startups, right? Like at the time Docker
is a startup. They can be way more agile
than a big company and so by virtue of
sort of like
being a separate entity uh we could be a
little bit more agile, also.
>> I mean, the earliest conception of this
project was you and two others kind of
hacking something together.
>> Yeah, it was a demo. I mean, it was sort
of a demo almost. It was like, "Look
look what we can do if we just smash a
bunch of existing open source tech
together.
>> Well, what did that demo do?
>> Uh I mean, it was basically like a basic
cube control.
It was like, "Hey, here's like here's a
container I built." I mean, at the time
you had to explain Docker to people. You
were like, "Hey, here's Docker. I used
it to like build this container image."
Um
and and then you could run it and deploy
it and see that it had gotten
distributed across a bunch of machines
and that you could, you know, load
balance to it cuz you you'd hit a single
endpoint and it would go, "I'm replica
one." And then you'd hit reload and go,
"I'm replica three." And, you know, so
it like showed that it was replicated
and then
um
basic health checking. So, like if you
killed it, it would come back and uh a
V2 to V or a V1 to V2 upgrade. That was
about it.
>> How How long did that that initial MVP
take to build?
>> Uh I wrote it in, I don't know, a little
under a week, maybe. Something like
that.
I mean, like I don't don't work on the
weekends, so maybe 5 days, 4 days, 5
days.
>> Did And did you drop all of your
existing work? Cuz I'm imagining your
you had existing project work and this
is kind of extra credit stuff that you
were working on.
>> Yeah, well, I mean, I wouldn't say I
I dropped it, but like in in a time
scale of that time scale, like
you can kind of like slack on it a
little bit. You know, like
like you could be sick for a week. I
mean, I guess the thing is like you
could be sick for a week, you know? And
I'm not saying that I That's not what we
did. That's not what I did, but like but
but there was enough flexibility in in
the system that like you could hack it
together. Um And I mean, believe me, it
was hacked together, right? Like every
possible shortcut to take and every And,
you know, I think one of the things I've
been good at historically is um
integrating other open source projects
together, seeing how you can take stuff
off the shelf and put it together. And
so, you know,
a lot of the nuts and bolts were
pieces that we could take from other
open-source projects and um
and kind of combine together with a
little with glue and glue code to
they'll you know to to give the feel of
it. So, that helps, too.
>> I think a lot of software engineers when
they hear this kind of story,
they think, "Oh, I have my existing
responsibilities and I can't necessarily
go off and build this thing, even though
I think it's a great idea." Do you have
any advice for someone who has that
opinion?
>> Yeah, well, I mean, I think that what
what even this I would say there's two
things two I have two answers to that.
Um one is advice that I've always given
to every single um
person that's ever worked for me, which
is
I believe you can hide
order 10% of your effort from your
management,
right? So, like
you know,
there's a there you have slack. You have
the ability to slack, no matter what,
right? Um
and you know, as you get a bigger and
bigger org, actually the percent that
what you can do with that 10% actually
increases. Um and a lot of really good
of really influential good ideas that
I've had have come out of that. I mean,
it's another I mean, it's kind of a flip
way of saying, "I want to empower people
locally to make local decisions that
they think are optimal for the business
without having to consult up the chain,
without having to ask permission,
right?
And you tell people while when you tell
them that, you're like, "By the way,
you're also going to make a bunch of bad
decisions in your going to waste a bunch
of time.
And so, like you have to be comfortable
with this idea of like, "I'm going to
try some ideas, some of them are going
to fail, some of them are going to
succeed. When I look back
retrospectively, the ones that have
failed were effectively a waste of
time."
Um
you know, and it might be the difference
between a exceeded expectations and a
met expectations,
right? Like you don't want to drop below
meets expectations, but like it might be
the difference between an exceeded
expectations and a meets expectations,
and you have to be comfortable with the
notion that
you're going to bet five times, and the
payout from one of them hitting is going
to be way better than the grinding to
get that exceeds every single time.
Um
and you know, I mean I I I think it's I
think there's equally valid paths where
you don't do that, right? And I think
that you have to be the right kind of
person who's willing to take that kind
of chance.
Um
so and then that's not everybody, and
that's okay.
Um
And I think the other side of it that I
but I always remind everybody also
though is like
you know, people say things like that to
me sometimes, and I'm like, "So, do you
play Call of Duty?
Do you watch Netflix?
Do you watch YouTube?" You know, because
like I'm pretty sure there's probably
10, 15, 20 hours in your week at least
when you're doing something that's not
work,
right?
And I can tell you in that time period,
I wasn't doing anything except for this
and work,
right? And a little bit of family, like
and sleeping.
Right? And so like sometimes it's also
about saying like, "Well, what are you
willing to give up?"
You know, to to have the space to do
that.
Um
and you know, I'm not a big like I've I
I I'm not a big like work all night kind
of person, but like it does mean like
maybe not going to watch YouTube for a
while, maybe not going to watch, you
know, sporting events for a while. That
makes sense. And I mean, on that second
point,
in this case, I mean, it was such a
the returns of this project were
exponential. They're obscene. I mean, if
you put in two times the the time for a
year, but you you get 20 times the the
impact. So,
I I it just kind of makes sense in terms
of investment of time.
>> also I think I mean, I found personally
that like
the it was addictive,
right? I mean, I think I benefited from
two things. One is I really like to
write code,
right? Like I I I enjoy it as an
activity.
Um
and uh uh and so like if I'm choosing
between Netflix and coding, I'm actually
pretty happy just coding.
You know, so that's a benefit um for me.
Um
and then for me anyway, like once people
start using it and they're excited about
the project and they're putting issues
on GitHub and all of this kind of stuff,
like I'm just addicted to it.
Like I just want to close that issue. I
want to help that person out. I want to
like I'm going to I'm going to go till
I'm falling asleep on my laptop. Um
and and that's just because that's I
enjoy that. Like that's why I'm in the
industry.
Um
so even in the moment I wasn't I mean,
you're I was definitely not thinking
about like, "Oh, here's this payout that
I'm going to get for the rest of my
career." Um
I was definitely in the like "Wow, I
just want to keep this thing going. I
want to keep this, you know, I want to
keep this rush going."
>> Well, cuz it sounds like it it took a
while for you guys to get buy-in from
leadership.
>> I think there was a solid 6 months of
going from
a very hacky prototype
to something that like legitimately we
thought somebody could take and use.
And laying down the right kind of
groundwork for that. Um
you know, there's a lot of little
details that you have to get right along
the way. Um
and and it's always nice also because,
you know, a lot of
uh
a lot of the people who we brought in in
the early days um had built similar
systems before.
And so they were having this
opportunity, this kind of clean It's
rare in your life as an engineer to get
a clean room opportunity to rebuild
something that you have ideas about how
it could be better. It's like getting a
second chance.
You know, and and so that was also I
think really attractive to people cuz
it's suddenly like
"Oh wow, like this is a clean room. We
don't have any users right now.
So like we don't have to be fixing bugs
cuz some, you know, big company is who
pays us a lot of money is asking for
something or whatever. We've got this
clean room time and
we've all spent a lot of time thinking
about what the system could look like.
And so now we get to like go and just
build the thing that we imagined.
>> You mentioned that first point on hiding
maybe 10% of your bandwidth from
management. And I mean that's that's
super interesting to me. What does that
look like in practice?
>> Um
well, I mean I think that it what it
means is that you should always have
sort of a like a side project that you
think is relevant.
Right? Like you should always have
something that is that nobody told you
to do.
But that you think is important that
you're working on.
>> I see. So it's kind of like I remember
Google, I don't know if they still do
this, but at the time there was 20%
time.
>> Yeah, that's similar to that kind of
idea. Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
>> Okay, so when you say when you say hide,
you don't mean hide, you say
manage expectations so that your manager
is also okay with you working on another
project.
>> Oh no, I actually do mean hide, right?
Like don't ask permission.
Right?
Like sooner or later you'll show it to
them.
But like it's pretty like you need a
solid, I don't know, couple months or
whatever to get to like a place where
it's something you could show to
somebody, right? And so like it's all
about saying like I'm not going to ask
permission.
I'm going to go build something that I
think is important and useful.
And then obviously when it comes time to
launch it or whatever or put it out
there, like then you do have to ask
permission.
Right? Um
and and so then yeah, you say like hey,
I built this thing. But but you've had
that time to like
get it from cuz I I I mean I don't know.
I feel like
it's hard to articulate the value of
something
like in a doc or in a PowerPoint. It's
way more effective if it's like a
running thing that you can like somebody
can interact with, right? So, getting
that time to basically build it up into
something that's real
and could ship. Cuz also like in some
sense your manager is always assessing
like, well, should you
spend your time on that or should you
spend your time on this, right?
And by building it, you kind of like
force their hand.
Cuz it's no longer like should you to
spend time building this or should I you
spend time building this? It's like,
I've already built this.
Like, do you want to ship it? And and
that's in some ways a much easier
decision. Like, I don't know about
easier, but like it's like it's not an
either/or, it suddenly becomes it's just
sort of about like is your idea good?
Right? Cuz the work is done.
>> I mean, in the happy path, I feel like
it's it's a great idea. You launch this
thing, has impact, it's great. What
about in the case that you work on this
thing and you didn't tell anyone about
it and then it
no one cares when you launch it or it's
not as good as we thought.
>> Yeah, and and then like that's the flip
side, right? Like
you have to be comfortable I mean, as I
said, like you have to be comfortable
with that idea that
um
you know, you're going to waste some
time. Uh and maybe it'll be a waste time
in the sense of like, wow, I could have
been like watching Netflix or, you know,
whatever.
Uh and I instead I wrote a bunch of code
that nobody liked. Um it could be
wasting time in the sense of like, wow,
I could have, you know, could have
gotten promoted. I could have done
enough work to get promoted and I didn't
because I thought this was the great
idea that was going to get me over the
hump, but it wasn't.
Um
and I think you just have to be
comfortable with that.
Like, you know, it's it's taking I mean,
it is taking a risk. It's not unlike in
some sense like
doing a startup or something like that.
It's taking a risk.
So, you know, I think I think and you
can't and you can't assume I think
sometimes people are like go into any of
these sorts of things and they're like,
oh, I will have the idea and it will be
amazing and then it will hockey stick
and like
I think if if that's your mindset when
you go in, you're probably setting
yourself up for some disappointment.
You know, you have to go in with that
mindset of like, I think this is good.
I'm going to try, but I'm okay if I
fail.
Right? Like I know that I may I'm making
an explicit choice here.
>> I also imagine at at some point at the
highest levels of uh engineering
ladders, you you need to take that risk
to get promoted to higher levels. For
instance, like if you're a staff
engineer or senior staff engineer and
you ask your manager, how do I get
promoted? They'll often tell you, you
need to figure out what that project is
cuz I don't I can't just hand this to
you cuz it's starting to become more
ambiguous.
>> Oh, yeah, for sure.
>> Yeah, I could totally see that this
becomes a necessity at some point. Uh if
you want to kind of grow and I mean this
this project also got you promoted as
well at Google, right? From uh from
staff at some point.
>> Uh yeah, I know I've certainly my career
absolutely benefited from the success
there. Absolutely, right? But uh and I
think you're right that like there
there's also this aspect of at a certain
point like
you're just expected to be the person
who knows enough to come up with the
really good ideas.
A- and and that's just the expectation.
Like it's no longer about like can you
execute on the ideas that other people
give you? You know, and and and that's a
big that's a big part of it as well. And
I think there's also like dispro- I
mean, I was the other thing I tell
people sometimes when um they're
thinking about getting promoted is um
if you create the idea yourself
entirely, it's like blindingly obvious
that it was you who did it.
Right? If you succeed and have impact in
something that is a bigger project or
someone else's idea,
um you can still have a very successful
career, but it's a little bit harder for
it to like be directly attributable to
you.
Right? Um
and
but again, I mean, I I think that again,
it's it's a roll of the dice, right? And
so like at some level like there're
probably are people out there who've
tried over and over and over again and
just have never had the right idea.
Right? Or just had the right idea at the
wrong time. I mean, I think one of the
other things that is interesting about
innovation that is disruptive is that
it's a combination of
being the person who has the idea and
being in a time in which the idea can
take off.
Right? And it's So, you could have the
idea, but it could just be the wrong
time.
And it won't do the same and it won't go
in the same direction.
>> That point on promotions, I think I
mean, if you create the scope, not only
is it is it obvious that that the credit
should go to you, but it also feels kind
of permissionless. Like you don't need
to wait for
um I guess management or someone to give
you the opportunity. You can kind of
create it, and so you have a lot more
control in that in that process. One
thing on the the business strategy, I
guess before we leave that for
Kubernetes, is at that time, Borg to me
felt like a competitive advantage for
Google. Like some secret infrastructure
sauce.
I would have thought people would be
kind of worried about
giving away any part of that to the
industry. So, what was the the thinking
there? How how would you convince people
that hey,
it's okay?
>> Yeah, I mean, I think that there was a
little bit of that.
Um
and I think you know, to to be a little
bit make it into a little bit of a joke
or whatever, I sort of one of the things
I said to people was, you know, it's not
like you Men in Black flash people as
they leave Google.
Right? Like, you know, it's not like
everybody comes to Google and they just
stays there forever, right? And so, and
in fact, as we talked to people at
Facebook, as we talked to people at
Twitter, we talked to people at other,
you know, scale-out tech companies, like
they were all building this stuff.
The the this it wasn't really a secret.
And there was also, I mean, like Mesos
at the time was
you know, not the same, but similar and
like you could just see that there was
going to be an open and and so in some
sense you part of the argument was like
look there's going to be an open source
solution. Do you want it to be one that
we can influence or not? It's not like
do you want there to not to be an open
source one or not? It's there's going to
be an open source one.
Do you want it to be ours or do you want
it to be someone else's?
And it's just reframing the choice,
right? And making it clear that people
understand that that is the choice,
right? That that you don't get to choose
the proprietary option because it's just
not viable.
>> When you were building that that MVP for
the orchestrator,
well, how did you decide cuz there were
no customers or anything like that? So
how did you decide this is the minimum
set of features that we need for this to
before we launch it?
>> Sure. Well, I mean I think absolutely,
you know, we benefit from the fact that
there were three of us working on it,
right? So Craig was a a great product
manager and Joe was a great engineer and
and and fantastic at API design. Um and
and I could write code fast basically I
think is sort of the the the you know,
like if I if I had to sort of stereotype
all of us, you know, that's the like
Craig was the product business guy and
Joe is the like I know how to design
really good at design kind of person and
and I was basically like I can hack
prototypes like there's no wasted like
no tomorrow.
Um and
and and I think we reflected a lot about
our own experiences.
Um and also we had seen the pain of
people deploying um into traditional EVM
infrastructure and so we had that that
kind of knowledge of the pain that
people are going through. And then
you know, at the time there were people
like Netflix who were talking about
immutable infrastructure and they were
kind of advancing some of the similar
some similar concepts.
And so there was also kind of like a
broader movement happening that we were
taking part in. Um and so
you know, obviously there were no there
were literally no customers, but in some
sense there there were customers. They
just weren't customers yet.
Um so it's not like creating something
brand new, I guess is in some sense.
Right? Like Like I feel I really don't
feel like Kubernetes was something that
was brand new.
I feel like it was a coalescing of a lot
of ideas that were kind of circulating
in the in the industry at the time. And
it just became an anchor point and a
really good expression of those ideas.
>> So when you talk about I guess you wrote
a lot of code quickly,
it did you write most of the code I
guess for this initial initial MVP?
>> Yeah, I I don't know what the number is,
but high 80 high 80s percentage maybe
more of of the original code. Um and I
think I'm still number I mean I haven't
contributed significantly to Kubernetes
in a while and I'm still I think number
five on the all over overall
contributor, you know, overall
contributor list on the GitHub commits.
And I was never I was number one for a
long time.
>> I mean after writing that much code for
Kubernetes, which part of this system
was the hardest to build?
>> I I think I'm going to say like cuz I
don't think any of the specific code was
that hard. Um
I think that the
core the hard part was the decision that
we made early on that it was going to be
a really loosely coupled system.
And so it's very
um
which is great for resiliency. Like we
made this decision around very loose
coupling, a lot of independent actors
taking actions. There's all these
control loops running all over the
place.
Which is really good for resiliency.
Um
but when things go wrong, it's really
hard to figure out
why they went wrong. Because you've got,
you know, 15 different processes that
are all having to work together to
achieve an outcome. And so you can see
that the outcome wasn't achieved.
Right? But then you're like, okay, but
like what happened?
And now I have to sift through a bunch
of different logs and a bunch of
different operations of executables and
sort of reconstruct in time what
happened and and especially early on we
didn't have very good
we didn't have very much consistency
around logging, we didn't have very good
consistency about event like events and
things like that. Um
And so I think the hardest part and I
mean it's the hardest part of anything I
guess, but like it's when something went
wrong figuring out like why it went
wrong.
>> Because your logs are all distributed
everywhere and
>> Yeah, and everything's out of time sync
and I mean and hopefully you logged the
right things, but a lot of time early on
like you didn't log it. Like you know,
and and and and because it's a
interaction effect
it's hard to reproduce.
Um often times it's hard often times
it's hard to reproduce the problem. Like
if it's a problem reproduces easily then
it's pretty easy to fix even if you
don't have the logs because you just go
and add the logs and then you do it
again and you see what happens. Um
But for problems that are transient
uh that because of it's just, you know,
race condition between two or three
different things happening, you can go
in and add the extra logs, but then you
have to figure out how to make it
happen.
Right? Um and that's that can be pretty
tricky. Um and also I mean I'll say the
other thing is like we were all learning
Go.
So maybe the other thing was like
there's some gotchas in Go lang and we
were all kind of like learning all the
gotchas on the fly.
>> I would have thought there's something
that's controlling everything, right?
Like there's some leader or maybe some
nodes that are looking at one of them to
kind of coordinate everything. Like
leader election, if the leader goes
down, I would have thought would be some
really challenging problem.
>> Yeah, I mean well, I think what what the
reason it wasn't that big a deal was
because
um
we relied pretty exclusively on etcd to
to do that for us.
>> Also, etcd is another
framework or open source?
>> Uh yeah, etcd is an open source I mean
it's kind of really part of
Kubernetes now, but at the time it was a
um
it's a a raft raft-based consensus uh
system key value store.
Um and so it was a pre-existing piece of
software that that CoreOS had written um
that implemented the raft protocol cuz
at the time like cuz Paxos is was the
original for this and Paxos is really
hard to implement cuz the algorithm is
really complicated
uh and nobody understands it. Well,
probably somebody understands it, but
not a lot of people understand it. So
then
but it's provable, right? Um
and then right around that time frame
people had come up with raft, which is a
provably correct consensus algorithm,
but it's way easier to implement. etcd
implemented the raft protocol and then
gave you this consensus reliable um
store so that uh
you could do um
uh it had you had multiple replicas and
it would do it would do the consensus
there and it doesn't do leader election
exactly, but it allows but it gives you
enough primitives that doing leader
election is relatively
um straight forward. Um
and and I guess I would also say that I
mean two things about that. One is we
decided to force all of the access
through an API server.
So no nobody had and this was actually
something I pushed really hard initially
um but we I think we had general
agreement, but I definitely pushed for
it um was that nobody got to use store.
Everything had to be remote store.
Like nobody got to write stuff to disk
themselves.
Every every piece of the system had to
use the API server and had to use etcd
behind the API server as the way that it
did any sort of persistence.
>> What's the main benefit of that?
>> The main benefit of that is that
everybody gets to restart all the time
and they just come up and they work. So
you don't have to worry about
corruptions, you don't have to worry
about schema changes, you don't have to
worry about any of the like everybody
was effectively stateless
except for the database. Like there was
there's the etcd consensus algorithm
database
and that's the only place where there
was state.
And and so as a result
um
the the whole system was just a lot
easier to um
to to make stable. Um
the the downside of it is it it leads to
this like loosely couple like loose
coupling, right? Where it's a bunch of
independent loops mediating everything
through this storage layer.
Um
and and which made the debugging part
harder.
>> Right. So like the those are the sort of
the trade-offs is like if you have a
complete log of like I'm in
you know, if you think of it as a state
machine, like it's much easier to
understand where you are
and where you got to
if you're in a state machine.
Um
but state machines are a nightmare to
make reliable.
And so like they're easy to they're easy
to debug, but they're hard to make
stable. Whereas the system we built was
like designed to be stable
but hard to debug.
The trouble with the state machine is a
state machine says the world looks like
this.
And unless you get it exactly right
sometimes the world looks like something
you didn't imagine.
And at that point you're kind of screwed
because like your state machine doesn't
know what to do.
Right? Whereas because we have these
control loops that were based on a
desired state and a current state and
trying to drive the current state to the
desired state
like no matter where you woke up and
found yourself,
you kind of knew where you were supposed
to drive to. And that And that And
that's the stable part. That's the
stable part of it is that like it didn't
really matter what what where the system
got itself.
It was always trying to drive towards uh
the the desired state. You know,
inspired honestly a lot by like control
theory from robotics, actually. Like
>> Oh, like uh PID.
>> Yeah, the same same idea, right? Like,
you know, you could imagine if you tried
to write a PID controller to balance a
beam with a bunch of if else loops, it
like it just doesn't work very well.
>> And that this kind of reminds me cuz I
was reading like in some of the design
uh like a large I guess it's a feature
of Kubernetes is that it's declarative
rather than imperative. So, you kind of
just say, "I want this to be true. I
don't care how you get there." instead
of saying, "Just do X, Y, and Z." Um I'm
curious like the pros and cons of that
that design decision.
>> Um well, yeah. I mean, and that was
something that was happening broadly in
the industry. Like, that's a part of the
whole like infrastructure as code
movement that was happening at the time.
Um so, we're not the only ones who said
that, but we definitely embraced it. Um
I you know, I mean, I think the benefit
is, you know, you have clarity about the
way you want the world to work.
Right? It's not Like, if you if you if
you execute a bunch of instructions,
start this, run that, do this, like
you've done a bunch of stuff in pursuit
of some objective.
But you never wrote down what the
objective was.
Right? There's no record of like what
you were trying to achieve. I'm trying
to create a website. Well, you didn't
write that down. You just took a bunch
of steps.
Right? With a declarative with a
declarative approach, you actually write
it down. You say like, "I'm trying to
create a reliable website, and here's
what a reliable website looks like."
"Hey system, could you take the steps to
get there?"
Right? And so, you have that record. Um
and it obviously makes it easier for
things to be self-healing because if
you've written it down, now I know where
I'm supposed to go back if like if I get
perturbed from that state, if something
fails, if something restarts, well, I
know where I'm supposed to go back to.
Um
and similarly, like it has ans- it has
side benefits of like once I write it
down, well, I can apply code review to
it.
I can apply unit tests to it.
Like there's a lot of like the the
mechanics of how we do software
development that apply once you write
down that declaration.
Um so like a lot of those are the
benefits. I think the downside is
probably just complexity.
Right?
You know, in comparison to go and click
click click through a wizard or
whatever, you know, in a GUI. Um
learning and you know, everybody
complains about the YAML and I have to
learn all this stuff and you know, like
it does introduce a
a learning curve.
Um now, I think fortunately at this
point there's enough educational
material out there that it's not and and
GenAI, too, for that matter, that it's
not that bad a learning curve.
Um but certainly in comparison to what
people have done before, that's probably
the biggest downside. But I don't know.
I think that the upsides are
like up here and the downsides are like
way down like there's there's not a lot
of downside.
>> I see. Yeah, I could also see that being
helpful for I guess if you want to
optimize anything under the hood cuz
you're just making a promise to people
that this is going to happen, but if you
want to do it in a more efficient way or
something like that, then I guess it
just gives you all the the power to do
so.
>> Yeah, well, I mean, then that does make
things like machines failing a lot
easier.
Right? Because people don't say run this
on this machine. They just say, "I want
three of this to be somewhere."
And if a machine fails, well, it just
moves somewhere else, right? Because the
application isn't tied cuz I can't In
some ways, I don't know your intent,
right? If you log into a machine and you
start a process on that machine,
is it because you wanted a process?
Or is it because you wanted a process on
that machine?
I don't know. You didn't tell me.
And so if that machine fails,
what should I do? Well, I don't know,
right? But if I But if I know you said,
"Hey, I just want three replicas."
Well, then I know it doesn't matter that
it's on that machine. It could be on a
different machine. You'd be just as
happy.
>> I want to shift a little bit to kind of
when Kubernetes was was scaling and it
sounds like a a large part of this was
getting buy-in from other companies and
other people.
And so, you know, how how did you get
the buy-in from I know OpenShift was an
important part of Yeah, Red Hat
um and other companies that that joined
on. Like, how did you sell those
companies that Kubernetes is what you
want to use?
>> Well, I think I think for a lot of them,
especially in the early days, it was
kind of that quote around uh
undifferentiated heavy lifting.
Right? Like, they had some other
objective. Like, OpenShift was trying to
build a platform as a service.
Um or, you know, they were
you know, a lot of our early users who
were also contributors, you know, they
were trying to build some sort of
reliable web service or something like
that, right? And so, it was like, "Well,
we're going to have to build this thing
anyway.
Why don't we all build it together?
And we don't really care cuz we don't
think that's our value. Like, our we
don't think our value is tied up in that
layer.
So, we'll go contribute to your thing
cuz we're going to get more value out of
the collective than out of trying to do
it ourselves."
Um
and and so for a lot of the early
partners, that was a big part of the
argument was was like,
"Hey, we'll let you in." And And part of
that is making sure that they understand
that they're going to like that they're
going to be equal partners.
Right? Where it's not like cuz it's it's
one thing to take a dependency on
something, but then you're kind of like
taking dependency on someone else's road
map.
And so, it was really important also to
say, "Hey, like
you can come take a dependency on us,
but also we'll give you a seat at the
design table. So, when you need new
features,
you can, you know, contribute those
features. And And here's what we're
trying to achieve. And And And it
matches up with your road map. And you
know, that kind of stuff." So, I think
that's how we we approached it. And
then,
uh over time, you know, people became
more and more interested in being part
of it because there was a growing
ecosystem.
So, when you look at like networking
providers or storage providers, you
know, as their users were starting to
become Kubernetes users,
um they were motivated to make sure that
their networking system worked well with
Kubernetes or their storage system
worked well with Kubernetes and things
like that. Um so, that was sort of a
secondary layer of partner discussions
that we had.
>> Right. And that's not downstream of
becoming the dominant player. And I
guess that's validating the open source
strategy, which is you become dominant,
everyone's kind of got a
um integrate with you and all of that.
How did you prevent Google from
dominating in the the road map or I
guess controlling what Kubernetes would
be, given that it started at Google,
funded largely by Google?
>> Yeah, I mean, I think that was really
important. Um and and I think it was a
critical part of gaining adoption,
right? Um
and and and becoming the industry
standard and was was giving it
independence. Um and I think, you know,
there's two pieces to that. The first is
um getting it to foundation. So, the
creation uh it was only a year in that
we created the Cloud Native Compute
Foundation, that we donated all of
Kubernetes to the Cloud Native Compute
Foundation. Um and so, getting the
project, the logos, all of the legal
stuff, trademarks, all of that stuff,
um
into a independent software foundation
um with the Linux Foundation was
critical, right? Cuz cuz it's hard to
partner if you know, somebody else has
trademarks on the Kubernetes logo or
whatever.
Um
and then I think the other piece that
was important that came a little bit
later um
was writing down the governance rules.
So, you know, for the first time for
first for a few years, Kubernetes didn't
have any really governance rules written
down.
Um it was a mistake I would say, right?
Like we didn't realize how
it was really it was something we should
have done earlier, but we didn't. Um
and so we sat down in 2016 to write the
governance rules
um
and I think all of us were aligned and
on this idea that we didn't want any one
company to be able to take control of
the community.
Um and we really built the community and
the govern the rules of governance to be
democratic. Um
you know, we never I mean I think that's
an aesthetic from Craig and Joe and I.
We never set out to be like a benevolent
dictator for life style project. We
always set out to be a distributed
uh you know, distributed ownership
democratic kind of project. Um and we
codified we codified a lot of that into
the governance docs that you know,
continue to this day. So, um I think
both those things together really helped
make sure that it was a an industry
standard not a and not any one
particular company standard.
But also I think were critical to its
success. Like I think they're they're
they're jewels of each other, right?
Like you can't have one without the
other.
>> People wouldn't have come on if they
didn't see that it was uh governed well
and open.
>> Yeah, I mean cuz obviously like you're
thinking about adopting it or you're
thinking about you know, putting it in
your service like the thing the thing
you're worried about is like whose road
map am I betting on?
>> Um when you said governance, is that I
mean mean, that literally like uh like
when I think of government, like there's
a constitution somewhere?
>> That's literally what we wrote.
>> Did you write that yourself or is that
something that like lawyers do or
>> Uh no, no, we wrote it ourselves, yeah.
Um
in the span of about uh it was a couple
of free couple free fairly intense
meetings amongst amongst like six or
seven of us. We got together um
and uh
and just kind of talked it through.
And and and looked at a bunch of other
communities and kind of like what had
worked, what had not worked, what were
we worried about, what were we trying to
achieve.
Um some of it was codifying stuff that
already existed.
Um so we had some loose organization
stuff that already existed in sort of a
de facto way, but didn't it exist in a
explicit way.
Um some of it was, you know, uh we we
created the steering committee
uh that had never existed before, right?
And we just basically uh and we were
lucky, I think, that we were able to
gather
uh so the people that came together, we
called it the bootstrap committee.
Um
you know, we we were lucky in the sense
that we had enough people
in who kind of were
not who who the entire community would
look at as being leaders.
And and and they worked we weren't
fighting with each other, you know, we
weren't in fighting, so we were all kind
of aligned. And we kind of got
everybody. So we didn't have to be like,
oh, you know, we grabbed this side and
not that side. We kind of we grabbed we
were able in
it was like seven people, I think, seven
or eight people. Um
we were able to pull together
a group of people that really
represented everybody and that everybody
kind of all respected each other and
respected each other as leaders in the
space. Um and a lot of credit there, I
think, goes to I mean, everybody deserve
who is involved deserves a lot of
credit, but um
Sarah Novotny, who was the um
uh our community leader at the time
deserves I think a ton of credit for
bringing that bringing that thing
together.
>> When you look back on on Kubernetes, cuz
with an open source project, there's
obviously the the read aspect, which is
everyone can use and duplicate this code
and execute it. But there's also I guess
the writing part, which is people making
contributions.
What percent of the contributions
actually come from the community and
what percent is actually just the main
stakeholder companies just putting in
their code?
>> Um yeah, I don't have the specific
numbers for Kubernetes, but my
experience in open source says it's like
80 to 80 90% the core contributors.
And like less than 10%
other people. It It's It's It's hard I
think in general. It's really hard to
get people to contribute. Um part of it
is companies, honestly, right? Like you
know, companies like Microsoft, uh
we make a commitment to contributing to
open source. And so, you know, we at a
leadership level, we've decided that
this is something that we want to invest
in.
Um and so we're willing to have teams of
people who specialize in working in
upstream open source projects.
Um
but for a lot of users of Kubernetes,
you know, they're a retailer or they're
a banking industry or they're like
it's tech isn't their core thing that
they're doing. Tech is a means to an end
to deliver an app for their user. And in
that world, it's pretty hard to justify
well, I'm going to take
10% of my people and I'm just going to
do upstream open source contributions.
Right? Um and especially if the
leadership is like not a technical
leadership, and so they didn't
necessarily grow up in those
communities. And if you grow up in
finance, it's hard to explain like
what's the value of contributing to the
I mean, the value of taking the open
source is very clear, right? It's free.
Um but the value of contributing back,
it's harder to explain. And
um or legally, like I've we ran into
people even today. It's getting better I
think but like even today I've run into
people who say like we would really love
to contribute.
Our engineering leadership is aligned
that we would want to contribute. But
our legal team is worried that if we
contribute we'll be liable if we
introduce bugs.
Right? So like if
>> Would someone sue them or?
>> Yeah, I think that's what they're
worried about. I I don't it doesn't hold
water legally and I think the Linux
Foundation can give you plenty of like
case law and things like that to show
why it doesn't hold water.
Um
but sometimes that's enough to block
uh
someone from contributing.
Okay?
>> I I never thought someone would get sued
for adding a bug. I mean everyone adds
bugs on accident.
>> Well, but I mean but on the other hand
like if you write a proprietary piece of
software and you sell it to somebody and
it has a bug and it causes your house to
burn down. Like you can imagine you're
going to sue the you're going to sue the
people, right? So like
it is sort of a legit worry at some
level of like if I wrote the JPEG open
source JPEG library that ended up in the
smoke detector that caused the house
Yeah, like
you can sort of imagine the chain of
logic that gets you there. I don't think
it's true. I don't think it would hold
up. I think a lot of the licenses, you
know, a lot of the
open source licenses include
indemnification language that basically
says
if you use this you're using it under
your own risk and like you can't sue us
if it burns down your house. Um
but
I think that that's a worry for I mean
what I've heard No, I don't think. I've
heard from people that that that that
their companies do have that worry. Um
and again in some sense it's because
they're like well, what's the value?
If I see this potential risk and I don't
necessarily see the value. And I mean
and like also like again if it's not a
core thing, if you're not a tech
company,
you know, is that developer really
capable of like arguing with legal
arguing with legal about what you can
and can't do. Yeah, probably not, right?
Like they're probably just going to fade
away, right?
Um so, you know, there's that aspect
too.
>> I remember this is many years ago, I
read this blog post that OpenAI put out
before I think OpenAI was kind of huge
and it says, "Here's how we scaled
Kubernetes to 7,500 nodes or something
crazy." I forgot exactly
>> On ours, yeah.
>> Yeah, yeah.
And so, I I I want to know um you know,
there's this new
these new workloads coming in for AI.
There's training, which is this huge I
guess all at once workload and then
there's inference, which is latency
sensitive and
you kind of need it to to come out
instantly. I guess how does how has
Kubernetes adjusted over the years to
handle these kinds of workloads?
>> Yeah, I mean, I remember when you know,
like we couldn't really handle more than
about 100 uh more than about 100 nodes.
So,
uh it's definitely been a lot of
optimization in the in the core systems
and there's places where the
APIs were pretty noisy.
Um and we needed to reduce the noise
level or we needed to extract
components into in another component so
that you could scale etcd in particular
actually is one of the could be the main
bottleneck to that kind of scale. And
so, figuring out how to run etcd really
well is a core part of figuring out how
to run Kubernetes really well at scale.
Um
I I mean, I don't think it's that
different than like learning how to run
a database or anything else like that at
scale. Like large scale is just weird
and you just have to
you know, run it, see where it breaks,
figure out how to fix it, or well, rinse
and repeat, you know. Um
And uh I do think what's interesting is
that while, you know, AI training as an
example is is a really large large
cluster or scale kind of thing. Um
you know, I think by virtue of being in
the cloud, a lot of our users actually
have much much smaller clusters.
But lots of them.
Right? So, hundreds or thousands of
clusters where each cluster itself is a
little bit smaller.
Um and I think that's not something we
anticipated cuz we came from a world of
like physical data centers where
you know, you only want one because like
you don't want to have to set it up a
bunch of times, right? You just want to
set one up for the entire data center,
call it a day. Um but because of the
cloud, because AKS you know, you press a
button
pops up in 2 minutes, right? Like it's
really easy to get yourself a cluster.
So, people create lots of clusters. Um
and and so I think we've also invested a
lot in the Kubernetes community and in
Azure as well on um managing lots of
clusters. How do I manage clusters at
scale? Um
you know, I think one of the jokes we
sort of like we spent a lot of time
talking about containers as replacing
snowflake servers.
Not snowflake the company, but like you
know, specially handcrafted servers.
Um
and now we just have a bunch of
snowflake clusters. So, the VMs all look
the same, but the clusters are all
weird. So, like we have to
provide people with tools to make sure
that the monitoring software is the same
on all of them and that the you know,
all of the Kubernetes versions are the
same and like you know, all this admin
users are the same and like all this
kind of stuff, right?
Um so, that's another aspect of scale
out that I think we didn't anticipate
that we had to go and and build, which
is num number of clusters as opposed to
size of cluster.
>> I always hear in the news that I mean,
this the anticipated scale is even
higher than today's unprecedented scale.
And I see people are purchasing GPUs
like crazy.
I'm curious, is there any upper bound
where Kubernetes just
it cannot handle that that um
that load? Like, let's say you you 10x
it from where it is today.
Is it Is it going to break down at some
point and you need something more
custom?
>> Uh well, I mean, I think it all comes
down It all comes back to the to the to
the storage layer that cuz everything
again cuz there was this design decision
that everything routes around the um
the storage layer.
Um everything else is basically
horizontally scalable. So, you you have
more API requests coming in from more
nodes, well, you just need more API
servers.
Um you know, you want to do scheduling
faster, well, you need to just have more
schedulers.
Um
so everything else more or less you can
just horizontally scale out.
Um
it's the it's it's the storage layer
that is the is the the bottleneck. Um
and that's where the work comes. And so,
you want to say go 10x up, well, you're
going to have to probably figure out um
if you can make etcd scale that way or
if you need to replace etcd with
something else that has the same
characteristics but can operate at
scale. Um
So, so I don't think there's anything
like inherent in the design that would
prevent it. Um but obviously
you know, there's a famous quote that
that every time you change an order of
magnitude, the problem moves. Um and so,
I think that's really true. Is every
time you increase by an order of
magnitude, what you thought was the main
problem is going to become easy and then
like the problem moves somewhere else.
So, you were never constrained, now
you're CPU constrained. You were never
constrained, now you're network
constrained.
>> Yeah, that'll be cool to watch how I
mean, cuz it seems like everyone wants
to
>> Yeah, I think it's definitely it's
definitely the case that people continue
to try and push the limits of scale. Um
and uh
but I think like anything else, like
when there's motivation
people go and figure it out.
All right, as long as there's not
something inherent in the design.
>> But the last part of this conversation,
I just wanted to reflect over your
career a a bit and maybe ask you a few
questions about things, and
uh you mentioned that you had a PhD in
robotics, and I hear a lot of people say
they don't recommend PhDs. Some people
do. I'm curious what your take on on
getting a PhD is.
>> Yeah, that's probably like like if I had
to have a top 10 questions or top five
questions that people ask me, uh that's
definitely in the top five top 10
questions. Um and I guess I'll I'll I'll
answer it with two different stories.
Um
one story is that uh
at one point in my career I ran into a
guy at same company, this guy who I went
to undergrad with.
Um and he'd gone off and done startups,
and you know, done the tech industry
thing, and ended up in the same company
that I was working at. And I'd gone off
and done my PhD, and come back into the
industry, and and we were the exact same
level. We graduated the exact same year,
same degree, and we were at the exact
same level in this company. And so I
guess that's one way of me saying like,
"Eh?"
You know, like it probably doesn't
matter. It probably doesn't matter one
way or the other. Um
but I'll also turn it around and say,
"A, I had a lot of fun."
Right? So like I had a lot of fun doing
a PhD in robotics. So
that's worth it to me. Um
and then two, I think I learned a lot
about how to um I think from the PhD and
my PhD advisor, I learned a lot about
how to write and put my ideas forth in
both written and presentation form.
That you don't necessarily learn in the
industry.
Um and I think that benefited me. I
think I benefited my ability to, you
know, argue We talked about that
six-month period where we were arguing
for like why we should be allowed to
open source this thing.
Um
I think the thing The skills I learned
in terms of presentation and in terms of
writing
um benefited me uh during that time. Uh
and have continued to benefit me.
Um
and and then I think
you know, when I went out as a professor
for a couple of years, um teaching CS
101 and having to like explain stuff to
students who didn't really know anything
about computers,
um
I think really helped me organize the
the in the initial parts of the
Kubernetes project so that somebody
could learn about Kubernetes cuz people
were coming in and being like, "What is
a container? What is orchestration? How
do I do this?" Like there's a lot of
like just teaching that you had to do.
And and I think that experience as a
professor thinking about how do I teach
students something really helped me do a
good job um
with you know, teaching Kubernetes to
people. Um and so I think those things
were really beneficial. And so I guess
there's there's you know, the two
different arguments which is one is like
it doesn't matter. The other is I
learned a ton of stuff that I think was
pretty useful to my career.
Um and I had some fun.
>> Earlier you said uh top questions that
people ask you and I'm kind of curious,
what's the top question?
>> I think the one the other one that I get
a lot um
is uh
how do I know what I should learn?
Like a lot of a lot of especially when I
talk to the interns for the first couple
of years,
you know, a lot of the questions are
right revolving around like "AI seems
really hot right now, but I'm really
interested in systems. Like should I
like go learn AI cuz it's hot or should
I learn systems cuz I think systems are
interesting?" Actually kind of don't
care what you learn. I care that you're
learning.
Um and and so the most important thing
is to find something that you're excited
about and energized about
um because you know, you'll do that
instead of watching YouTube. Uh
you know, so if you're not excited about
AI, like well, you're probably not going
to do a very good job learning AI. Which
means that you're kind of going to waste
your time.
Um but if you're really excited about
systems, you probably put a lot of
passion and energy into it. And you
know, we still need systems engineers.
Like so,
um
I you know, I think that's the that's
kind of a pretty popular question. I
think there's a lot of I I sense anyway
a lot of like
fear of making the wrong decision.
And,
uh
I will tell everybody like there was no
plan.
I've never had a plan for my career.
Like, never ever ever.
Like, I've always just chased after
things that I thought were useful and or
fun and interesting.
Um
and
uh and, you know, obviously like that
can work out badly for people. I'm sure
it's good to have a plan probably for
some people, but like I also want to
make sure people understand that like
when you look back
sometimes the things you think were
mistakes or dead ends, like
actually were critical things that
taught you stuff.
Um
and so like worrying about did I choose
the wrong thing? Am I going to choose
the wrong thing? Like, eh,
as long as you're learning, you're
probably doing okay.
>> I mean, what you're describing it
reminds me of I don't know if you've
seen that Steve Jobs commencement
speech, but he
he literally says exactly that. You
wrote down somewhere I I don't fully
remember where you wrote this down, but
I have this in my notes. It says,
"The inevitable trajectory of software
is death."
And I just can't imagine Kubernetes
dying, but I how do you see that
happening and you know, what what do you
think about that if it did?
>> I mean, I definitely stick by that uh
that statement. Um
Although I think that the the the the
the sense before I said that was you
really should never fall in love with
your software
because the inevitable
trajectory of software is death. I am
It's which means don't stick with it
don't stick with it past when it's
dying, right? Um
like you should always be willing to
throw away stuff. Just don't stick with
it just cuz you wrote it. You should
always be willing to throw it away.
But, like obviously I think if you look
historically across the industry, it's
it's true, too, right? Like like
Um and and quite frankly, like even
within Kubernetes, like
the source code that I wrote has been
rewritten a number of times.
Um
over the 10-plus years history of the
project. Um
so, what does it look like? I mean, I
think it looks like uh
something coming along that achieves
similar things, but easier with more uh
you know, you with with less complexity
and and more utility. Um and and I think
that
you know, I can imagine what that looks
like. Like I think some of these natural
language stuff, if you could actually
really get it to be an interface that
worked 100% of the time, like obviously,
it's way easier to come in and say
I would like a reliable web service than
it is to say "YAML YAML YAML YAML YAML."
You know, I I think sometimes I I think
it's sort of your two different
trajectories. Like sometimes the
trajectory is
it it goes away. Sometimes it just
becomes so hidden that nobody sees it.
Right? Like underneath Linux, there's
I mean, excuse me, underneath
Kubernetes, there's Linux. And
underneath Linux, there's a processor.
But, you know, people don't pay much
attention to that. Um
and there's a lot of attention now on
AI, and underneath a lot of the AI is
Linux, but it could be that people focus
so much on the AI that they forget about
the Kubernetes part.
Um
and I think that's happening already,
honestly. Like I feel like
if I look at the volume of changes and
things like that, like I think it's you
know, I think we've sort of plateaued in
terms of like the amount of change
that's driving through the system. Um
stuff needed to support AI is kind of
like the
exception to that category.
Um
but, you know, I I I
I'd be shocked. I mean, I guess I'll put
it this way. Like let me take the long
view and say
in 100 years,
is Kubernetes still going to be running?
I'd be pretty surprised.
Right?
It's hard to imagine, right?
Um that that that would be true. I mean,
I don't know. We haven't had computing
systems for long enough to maybe know
for certain.
Um
and there are things that we still use.
I mean, there is some stuff that we
still use from back then. Plugs are
still the same shape-ish, stuff like
that.
Um
so maybe.
But even like something like x86, like
if you'd asked me 6 years ago and said,
"Is the x86 processor going away?"
I'd say like, "Well, maybe on I mean,
obviously on mobile it did, but like in
the server?
Maybe not." Um but now two things have
happened. One is all the processing is
on GPU now.
And two, like arm 64 is now pretty
important platform on the server for
energy usage and other reasons, right?
And so
it's pretty dangerous to predict the
future cuz like
it has a tendency of show up sooner than
you you you predict. So, or or longer
than you predict, too, right?
Self-driving cars, like I've heard I've
heard self-driving cars were 5 years
away for like the last 15 years.
>> Yeah. Uh,
me too. I I don't know if you read books
for career's sake, but if you do, is
there a book that impacted your career
the most?
>> Well, I mean, I would say like early on
the book that that impacted my career
the most was a book uh was the gang of
four book. Was it software engineering
designs and patterns or whatever? Like
it's a software engineering book.
>> I I see it. It's design patterns,
elements of reusable object-oriented
software.
>> Yeah, there you go. So, that like early
on that was a very influential book.
It's like a late '90s or mid '90s kind
of book. Uh there's a much more recent
book called uh Leadership on the Line
that as I've become sort of a large org
leader, that's uh I really like that
book. And then there's this What's this
book? It's called I think Five
Dysfunctions of Teams, I think. That's a
really good book, too, for uh from a
like a how teams operate perspective.
>> If I'm understanding if you're an if
you're an engineer,
check out that first book. If you're a
manager or a leader, check out the
second two books. Yeah, that's probably
about right. Yeah, I think that's I
think that's right. And then, you know,
it's an evolution over time, right? So,
like, maybe you'll do both.
Uh last question for you is
um if you could go back to yourself when
you just graduated college and give
yourself some advice,
what would you say?
>> Uh keep better notes.
You know, I feel like there's a great
MBA thesis or a great like book
in the whole Kubernetes journey and
beyond and like
I you know, like I don't I just don't
have enough notes to
uh to to do that, to write it down. You
know, I like we we went through a lot
like a lot of different stuff happened,
and I remember some of it, and I don't
remember a lot of it, and it would I
would have been nicer if I'd kept better
notes, I feel like.
>> All right. Well, well, you got all the
code there. Maybe an LLM can parse it or
something. You can reach out
>> more It's not so much about the notes
part. It's not so much about the code
part. It's like all of the Like the
stuff you were talking about, like all
the partner discussions and all of the
like interpersonal stuff and, you know,
all that kind of stuff. And like I
remember a lot of it, but I don't
remember all of it.
>> Cool. Well, thank you so much for your
time, Brendan. I really appreciate it.
>> Yeah, for sure. Thank you.
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed, and I
finally have a prototype, so I'd love to
show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic, and I
couldn't find anything like it on the
market, so that's why we built it. I'll
put a link to the keyboard in the
description. You can take a look and
learn more about the project there. We
could definitely use your support. Also,
if you have any feedback for me about
the show, I'd love to hear it. Comments
on YouTube have led to guests coming on
like Ilya Grigorik and David Fowler. I
wasn't aware of them until someone
dropped a comment. Also, feedback in the
comments helped me learn to reduce the
number of cliff hangers in the intros.
So, your comments definitely make a
difference. Please keep letting me know
what you'd like to see more of in the
show, and I'll see you in the next
episode.